[Music]
this program is brought to you by
Stanford University please visit us at
stanford.edu
all right so this is then
um the
final
class in quantum mechanics that's of
course wrong we will continue with some
quantum mechanics when we get to Quantum
field Theory
but the last of a uh of a
sequence and I think the most important
okay let's uh the most important two
subjects that we can do in quantum
mechanics to finish the subject up is
the harmonic oscillator and angular
momentum let's see if we can Fe squeeze
it into two
hours all right
so the harmonic oscillator is of course
basically a particle the mathematical
structure of
it is the particle moving on a line
under the influence of a force the force
being the restoring Force the hooks law
restoring force of a
spring that's the mathemat well that's
that's a physical example of a harmonic
oscillator there are many many examples
of harmonic oscillators in physics in in
fact really almost any system if it has
a stable equilibrium of some sort and
you disturb it a little bit it will
oscillate about the minimum this about
the uh about the stable
Point examples
are a weight hanging from a
spring okay
so the ceiling a spring a
eight assuming it we assume of course
not the assume I think we can prove for
the case of an ordinary spring that the
weight the
Mass finds an equilibrium position it
finds an equilibrium position at the
position in the gravitational field in
the vertical place here where the
gravitational force down exactly
balances the spring Force up the
gravitational force is constant doesn't
depend on how high the spring how high
the mass is the gravitational force but
the spring Force varies from nothing
when the spring uh is
unstretched and gets bigger and bigger
as the spring is stretched and so at
some point an equilibrium is found
between the spring force and the
vertical downward force of gravity and
that's the equilibrium position at that
point the mass can just sit at rest with
no uh no motion whatever but then then
if we disturb it a little bit it will
oscillate back and forth or up and down
in this case and execute harmonic
oscillations if we ignore friction air
resistance and um uh nonideal behavior
of the spring it will execute genuine
harmonic
oscillations meaning that it will
vibrate back and forth with a s pattern
s and cosine pattern that's the
classical description of it there are
lots of other examples of harmonic
oscillators um an example very important
example in physics is waves wave motion
if you stand at a particular point and
you watch a wave going past you of
course it oscillates up and down it
could be a water wave water waves are
not ideal harmonic oscillators they're a
little more
complicated but nevertheless you know if
the wave is moving past you and you
stand there and watch it it just goes up
and down the same way as this does and
so that's another example of a harmonic
oscillator sound waves
vibrating again say not watching with
your eye but listening with your ear
again a typical sound wave of a given
frequency is again a harmonic oscillator
there's all kinds of harmonic
oscillators in nature the mathematics of
them is all the same
so we choose to concentrate on one
example just uh the spring vibrating up
and down but the mathematics applies
very very
widely and in fact the mathematics
continues to apply widely when we go to
Quantum Mechanics so by quantizing the
simple system now of course no genuine
spring with an ordinary Mass attached to
it has any reason we would never have
any reason to want to quantize it in
practice it's too heavy for quantum
mechanics to matter quantum mechanics
does describe it but for ordinary heavy
masses and typical spring constants that
you would encounter if we went into the
laboratory here and got a spring out
quantum mechanics would be completely
unimportant or the corrections of
quantum mechanics the classical
mechanics would be completely
unimportant but
nevertheless uh the it's worth taking
this as an
example subjecting it to the rules of
quantum mechanics and then it really
does apply to all sorts of very much
lighter
systems not uh a heavy kilogram mass
hanging from an ordinary spring but for
example molecular motions molecules have
equilibrium positions the atoms have
equilibrium positions if you disturb the
atoms a little bit they vibrate about
the equilibrium positions and again they
describe harmonic oscillators for those
things uh quantum mechanics is important
so uh we take this as a as a
model and subject the physics of it to
Quantum Mechanics all right let's uh
let's
begin with the hamiltonian
describing the mass on a spring in fact
let's begin with the lran it's a good
place to start the lran is
12 the mass time the velocity squared
and let's call the displacement from the
equilibrium position let's call it X
even though on this picture here it's
sort of the y-coordinate let's call it
X and uh x dot is the time derivative of
x that's the velocity
squared that's the kinetic energy now um
it is always
possible to absorb into the defin
definition of X the mass I will do so
just to make a sort of standard
oscillator
uh where the mass is equal to
one I can always do that even if the
mass is not equal to one all I have to
do is Define a new coordinate for the
moment let's go over here and call it y
take y to be equal to the square < TK of
M *
x what is y^ 2 Y do^ 2 Y do^ 2 is equal
to M * x do^ 2 so if I chose to work
with a y coordinate instead of the x
coordinate it's really just a change of
units if I decide to change units from y
to X or from X to Y then y^2 is equal to
MX do2 and I could call this just 12 Y
do^
2 and get rid of the mass Al together
let's do it it it um it will simplify
many of our
equations
okay good now that I have exhibited how
to do it in terms of a new variable
called y let's just call the appropriate
variable X all I have to do is get rid
of the mass here and remember that the
new X x
coordinate is just the old x coordinate
time theun of M good so we get rid of
the mass in that way the mass plays no
special
role the important quantity is the
spring constant but again I'm going for
our purpose is to to set the spring
constant uh moment for the moment let's
see shall I call the spring constant one
no let's not call a spring constant one
I'm going to call a spring constant
Omega
squared all right so the spring constant
how do how does the um this is lran not
the uh not the
uh
uh not the energy the lran this is
L minus this is the kinetic energy minus
the potential energy what is the
potential energy when you displace a uh
an oscillator away from its equilibrium
position well it increases if you
displace it one way the energy it
increases if you displace it the other
way in either direction that you
displace it it the potential energy
increases that's why it tends to come
back to the
origin and so the natural expression is
proportional to the square of the
displacement if the potential energy was
just proportional to the displacement
itself it would increase in One
Direction increase in the positive in
One Direction increase in the negative
in the other direction that's not what
we want we want something which
increases in both directions when we
displace this object and the natural
thing to write down is something
proportional to X
SAR the coefficient in front of x s
is we can name it anything we want but
the standard ter the standard name is to
put a factor of a half there and then
the spring constant K but I'm going to
call the spring constant Omega
squared Omega is in fact the uh the
frequency of the oscillator this is the
lran let's just very very quickly work
out the equations of
motion remember what we do we take the
partial derivative or the derivative of
the lran partial derivative lran with
respect to x dot that has a name it's
the canonical momentum conjugate to X we
take partial of L with respect to x dot
that is just equal to x dot in this case
no Mass because I've set the mass equal
to
one and then we time differentiate
that that gives us X double dot and we
set that equal to the partial derivative
of L with respect to X do I have that
right or do I have the sign wrong uh I
think I have the sign
right that's partial derivative of L
with respect to X and what is that
that's Omega
squar uh that's minus Omega 2 x well
this is just FAL ma mass is set equal to
1 here's the acceleration and it's equal
to minus the thing that I've called
Omega 2 * x what does the minus sign do
doing
there why is it minus anybody know it's
a restoring force that means if you
increase X in One Direction the force
will pull you back and that's what the
minus sign is there okay so that's the
equation of motion x dot = minus Omega
2 - Omega 2 x and the solutions to the
equations of motion are SS and
cosiness the Sol solution of this kind
of equation is just X is equal to a *
cosine Omega T same Omega plus b time Co
time sin Omega
T that's the general solution of the
harmonic oscillator signs and cosiness
and this frequency here is just this
Omega the point is when you
differentiate twice you pull out a
factor of Omega squar okay so that's the
classical harmonic
oscillator all right to go to the
quantum harmonic oscillator the first
thing we want to do is well we have
several steps that we have to do we
first have to construct a space of
States a space of
states and the space of states or a
vector space describing the states of
the system the vector space for particle
moving on a line is just the functions
of x s of x
which is the amplitude to find the
particle at position
X defined in such a way that s star of x
* s of
X is the probability density to find the
particle located at a position X the
probability density the probability per
unit
interval this is the probability density
P of
X and and the space of states or the
vector space describing um the quantum
mechanics is just the vector space of
the function's side all right that's the
first step we have we now have a sort of
kinematics we now have a um a
specification of what the states of the
system are next step is to find a
hamiltonian if we want to know how for
example two questions we might ask how
does the state Vector change as a
function of time to know that we have to
know the
hamiltonian or not or but another
question we might ask is what is the
energy levels what are the possible
energies of the harmonic oscillator and
the possible energies of the harmonic
oscillator are also
determined are also determined by the
hamiltonian so to get started with
anything useful we have to we have to
have a hamiltonian
for that we go back to the classical
good just just close it for that we have
to go back to the
lran and apply the standard rules to the
lran to find the hamiltonian I'll just
remind you what they
are the hamiltonian is just
equal well before you do that you have
to define the canonical momentum
conjugate to X that's just p
and canonical momentum is partial
derivative of L with respect to x dot
that's just x dot in this case very
simple p is equal to x dot okay the
hamiltonian is PX dot this is classical
this is classical mechanics now
classical mechanics which was which two
quarters ago am my right two quarters
ago PX
dot minus l
okay px. minus L you know it's all let
me short circuit it the hamiltonian is
the energy and it's always given by the
uh kinetic energy plus the potential
energy the legrangian has minus the
kinetic energy sorry minus the potential
energy the hamiltonian has plus the
hamiltonian is just
12 m v^ 2 kinetic energy which in our
case is just just x do^
s plus the potential energy plus the
potential energy now means plus 12 Omega
X2 Omega 2
x^2 okay that's our uh uh that's the
energy but this has been expressed in
terms of
velocities the things which we know how
to turn into quantum mechanical
operators are the canonical momentum
canonical momentum has standard
interpretation as an operator in quantum
mechanics so let's reexpress the
hamiltonian in terms of canonical
momenta that's easy X do is equal to P
so the hamiltonian is
just2 p^2 + 12 Omega 2
x^2 and that's it that's the hamiltonian
a classical
hamiltonian and how do we make quantum
mechanics out of it we make quantum
mechanics out of it just by
understanding X as an operator X is an
observable the position of the of the
oscillator and P is an
observable both of them can be defined
through their action on S of X their
Herm Mission
operators and
uh their action on the state vectors of
the system are
straightforward okay we know what they
are
X just multiplies the wave function by X
I don't know how to write this except to
write that X acts on S of
x to give x * s of X that's a stupid
looking equation isn't it oh I know what
to do let's call this put a hat over it
to indicate that it's an operator and
let's put a k Vector around this to
indicate that it's a k and then we
shouldn't write equals we should write
that this corresponds
to multiplying s of X just by
X it takes every wave function and
creates a new wave function out of it X
multiplication by X is yeah isn't it
equal if you made out of the other yeah
but uh but then I will have to then I'll
have to make an operator out of this so
I'll just write the same thing over
again right the rule is uh
the rule is every time you see X think
of it as multiplication of the on the
wave function by X it's an operator and
it operates on the vectors which are
functions of X all right what about p p
of
course p on
S corresponds to minus i d by
DX now there's a factor of H bar isn't
there I'm going to put the H bars in at
the end let's set H bar equal to
one in the end we can figure out where
the H bars go by uh by dimensional
analysis all right so p on S is just
minus i d by DX on
s s of
X and now we can figure out what the
action of the hamiltonian is on a wave
function you simply multiply p by itself
and act on the wave function what does
that mean p by itself it just means that
you act once with p and then you act
again with P so let's figure out what
that
is uh let's write
h on
S corresponds
to
12 now let's first apply P once that's
minus i d by D
x s of
X but that's only operating with P once
we want to hit it again with P so we
just have to multiply it again not
multiply it but differentiate again
another factor of minus i d by
DX okay so we can write it minus i d by
DX acting on minus i d by
DX s of X and what is that that's the
second derivative of s with respect to
x minus I * minus I gives us a minus
sign - I * - I is the same as plus I *
plus I which is all together minus one
did you get that okay so this is minus
DC s by dx^ 2 - 12 DC s by dx^
2 incidentally why am I writing partial
derivatives here
I'm writing partial derivatives because
s in general also depends on another
variable the other variable
being time right so s in general will
depend on
time time is not an operator time
doesn't have the same status as X it
just says the state Vector changes with
time okay so uh so the partial
derivative indicates at a fixed time
all right that's 12 DC Side by dx^
2 yeah thank you negative
sign right that's the first term that's
the p^2 and then the second term is just
+
12 Omega
squar
uh x^2 * I of x
all
right that's the action of the
hamiltonian on S but what is the what is
the hamiltonian for the purpose of the
hamiltonian two purposes for the
hamiltonian one of them is to tell you
how the vector changes with time so
let's write out the schinger equation
the Schrodinger equation
I DC by
DT is equal to H SI that's essentially
the definition of the hamiltonian do I
have the sign right I always
forget minus i d by DX is momentum so
plus I D by DT yeah there's a there's a
sign difference between moment yeah
that's that's right I DCI by DT is equal
to H SI and now we can substitute this
we can substitute this and let's do
so
minus 12 DC Side by dx^
2 this yeah well that's a partial
derivative because it means you keep X
fixed all right you keep X fixed this is
the derivative of s of
X with respect respect to T but at fixed
X okay good this is the derivative of s
with respect to X at fix
t Okay so that's uh that's the first
term and the second term is
plus 12 Omega 2
x^2 * s of
X okay that's the shinger equation and
what it tells you is if you given SII
for example I give you SII at some
particular time the real and imaginary
part notice uh that the real and
imaginary part notice that the equation
is complex it has an i in it now that
means even if Sai was real at at the
starting point let's imagine that SII
was a real function at time T equals z
it will very shortly develop an
imaginary part
okay so the wave function when it varies
with time it's not it's not consistent
to to look for a real solution the
solutions must be complex because even
if it started real it would soon become
complex because of this I here so s is a
complex function of x and t and it
satisfies this equation this tells you
how it changes if at some instant of
time now I'm imagining that this is both
the real you know
it's a um a cartoon of a complex
function s of x s of X at an instant at
time T equals 0 this tells you how it
changes with time all right this is the
Dynamics this tells you how things
change with time tells you how things
evolve and you could solve it in a
number of ways uh one way of solving it
would just be to put it on a computer
start with s
update a little bit by calculating the
derivative once you calculate the
derivative you find out how it changes
in a small increment of time once you
know how it changes in a small increment
of time you add the incremental change
to sigh and you keep doing it over and
over and over again and whatever sigh is
it will do some interesting things it'll
move around somehow in fact it will move
around very much like a harmonic accor
back and forth back and forth back and
forth but that's not completely obvious
at the
moment the other thing you can do with
it is to calculate the energy levels to
calculate the energy en the energy igen
vectors and the energy igen
values uh it turns out and we'll we
we'll go through this I think um that
when you know the energies and uh energy
IG vectors and igen values you can work
out the time time dependence without uh
doing any differential equation that's
because you know the time dependence of
each energy I Vector but we'll come back
to that okay so let's concentrate on the
energy igen vectors the energy I vectors
themselves how do we find them we write
down the condition for an igen Vector
right the condition for an igen vector
is that H
times let's call it S Sub
e e for
energy a particular energy level
indicated by the value e here h on S of
E equals
e * s of
e or S of S Sub E I guess S Sub e
sub the sub e as I said here just
indicates which particular igen value
now this
equation does two things it solves the
or it it doesn't solve but it defines an
equation for the wave
function s
ofx it gives you an equation for that
but it also tells you what the possible
energies are I'll show you why in a
minute I'll show you why it picks out a
certain subset of values of e as
possible energy levels okay but let's
write this equation now in uh in terms
of s of X not as an abstract equation
but as an actual equation for
S all right what is h h is it's the
right hand side of the Schrodinger
equation up there - 12 DC s by dx^
2 this is H on
S or the representation of it in terms
of ordinary functions so I have
X
Plus Omega 2
x^2 s of
x equals e * s of x
looking for Solutions of that
equation which means both finding the
values of e which permit a
solution and also then solving the
equation tells you what the igen vectors
and the igen
values of the energy are okay now first
of all why would it
be that um
that not every value of e is a
possible energy igen value you can solve
this equation for any value of s of e
okay but let's look let's see shall we
um
uh
yeah all right I will tell you what
happens when you start looking for
Solutions if you start solving these
equation this equation you'll find out
that when you solve it for energy
E when you solve for S of X you
essentially find two solutions anybody
know why you find two solutions for an
equation like this because it's second
order because it's a second order
differential equation it has second
derivatives in it and whenever you have
a second order differential equation it
requ requires two pieces of information
to get a solution started and so there
are two independent Solutions of an
equation like this each
solution we'll see is exponential in a
certain way it varies one solution goes
like e to the some constant time x x^2
excuse me and the other one goes as e to
the same constant time- X x^
s there are two kinds of solutions ones
which blow up and ones which fall to
zero so for example imagine starting
this is a second order differential
equation you can start at any value of x
and you can start building yourself a
solution by simply numerically for
example building a solution you know s
of
X you can postulate a value for the
derivative of s of x
and start iterating your way to a
solution of the second order
differential equation generally speaking
if you pick an arbitrary value of the
energy of e what will happen is you will
find both kinds of solutions are there
to find a solution you will have to
superpose the two of them in general and
in particular one of the components of
the
solution will
uh will be exponentially
increasing exponentially
increasing out at
Infinity that's a terrible thing it
means that all of the probability is way
way out at infinite
distance in other words the probability
density is exponentially
increasing the relative probability of
being anywhere
relative to being very far away is zero
now that's not a good thing because the
energy contains X
squ if the probability is overwhelmingly
very far away it means it must mean it
has to mean that the energy is huge
because of this x squ
term and it would be
so there's something wrong with these
exponentially increasing Solutions the
right way to say it is the true space of
states is the space of states of square
integrable functions are functions which
are square
integrable namely they have the property
that s star s
DX is equal to one total probability
equal to
one that precludes functions which
exponentially blow up far away they
would not be square
integrable so the trick is to look for
values of
e
which allow Solutions in which the
exponentially increasing part is absent
there are certain discrete values of the
energy where the exponentially
increasing part just isn't there in
other words if you start at some point
and you start iterating your way to a
solution in both directions that's the
key that in both it's not hard to find
wave functions which decrease in One
Direction or the other direction but you
typically you get into a bind if you
look for Solutions which in decrease in
One Direction you find they blow up in
the other direction and vice versa only
at very select values of the
uh of the energies are the solutions
which increase in both
directions those select values are the
energy igen values of the harmonic
oscillator so let's see what we can do
let's see if we can figure out what they
are yeah there's another intuition let
me give you another intuition also uh
that uh that helps you understand the
harmonic
oscillator it's the uncertainty
principle the uncertainty principle
between X and
P classically how do I minimize the
energy I force both remember the energy
is positive definite or positive p^ s
and X squ are both positive classically
it's quite clear how to minimize the
energy you set p and x equal to Z but
Quantum mechanically that's too much
there's an uncertainty principle there's
an uncertainty principle which says that
you can't set both X and P equal to zero
you can try to find some
compromise where X is not too spread out
and P is not too spread out but you're
not going to ever find a solution where
both or or quantum mechanical wave
function where both X and P are both
equal to zero and so you have to find
some compromise because you had to
compromise it means that the ground
state energy the lowest possible energy
of the system will not be
zero both p^2 and
x^2 neither will be zero because of the
uncertainty uncertainty principle so one
of the things you should expect is first
of all that there are no negative energy
levels How can there be negative energy
levels when this is over when both of
these are positive they're both positive
operators thought of as operators
they're both uh only positive igen
values p^2 and x^2 are positive so there
are no negative energy levels and in
fact there is not an energy level with
zero energy the first energy level has
some positive energy all right I'm going
to tell you what the First Energy the
lowest energy level
is and uh by showing you a solution of
this
equation and maybe if I can figure out
how to do it while we're while we're
here I'll see if we can prove that there
isn't a lower energy level but
let me show you one solution of this
equation it's not with E equals 0 as I
said there are no Solutions with E
equals 0 because the energy because of
the uncertainty
principle okay let me show you a
solution there's a solution which looks
like e to the
minus I think it's Omega or let's let's
I can't remember if it's Omega or Omega
over
x² that's an interesting wave function
it's concentrated near the
origin so it does corespond to an
oscillator which is uh which is more or
less concentrated near the origin let's
see if we can figure out what the
hamiltonian does to it let's calculate
what the hamiltonian does to it the
first
term the minus
12 d by dx^ 2 let's first take that all
right let's different differentiate it
twice with respect to X that's the first
term in the hamiltonian here this is
s let's differentiate it once with
respect to X to differentiate it with
respect to X I have a feeling there's a
two here let's try it with a two I can't
remember uh let's put a two in if a two
isn't there we'll find it out and I'll
throw the I'll get rid of the two what
happens if I differentiate eus Omega
over 2x^2 once with respect to X
anybody want to try for
it let's see it will certainly give us
outside a minus Omega over 2
right then when you differentiate an
exponential with respect to an argument
you just get the exponential back eus
Omega over 2
x^2 but then you H you're going get x x
once F first derivative oh first first
derivative yeah
uh and that will give you an a 2X from
differentiating x s that will give you a
2X okay well it looks good the twos are
cancelling that's a that's a comforting
thing I'm not sure why I'm glad they're
cancelling but let's
uh let's
Rejoice I think is that it do I have it
right that's the first derivative that's
decide by
DX I hope now what happens if we
differentiate it again if we
differentiate it again we get two
contributions one we're differentiating
a
product right we're differentiating a
product the first term comes when we
differentiate the first factor in the
product okay this is DCI by
DX if I differentiate it again I get two
terms one of them just comes from
differentiating that that's minus Omega
eus Omega /
2x^2 the derivative of Omega X is just
Omega okay what happens if I
differentiate the other Factor the other
Factor will give me minus Omega X and
then the derivative of this with respect
to X but we've already figured out what
the derivative of this with respect to X
is it's just multiplication by minus
Omega X so that gives us I think Plus+
Omega 2 x^2 * eus Omega / 2
x^2 that's it that's the second
derivative with respect to um with
respect to x
s okay so that's the first Factor next
plus 1/2 I I have a feeling I'm going to
be sorry that I uh threw away that
1/2 yeah it does look like I wanted the
um well we'll figure it out okay then
there's + 12 Omega 2
x^2 do I have the sign wrong I want that
an overall minus sign yeah I think I
have the overall sign wrong I want
min-2 of the second
derivative
okay
ah the sign is
right let's see
when I differentiated once it gave me a
minus sign yeah okay the thing on the
left hand side that you got there is
just the second derivative yeah it's
just the second derivative so you still
have a minus a half to multiply right
right oh good good good we still have
minus a half good so let's let's put in
the minus a half all right so that will
give us a plus am I right I don't want
to disturb it unless I know what I'm
doing I think uh I should write this
being plus a half good so this should be
plus a half and this one should be minus
a half
right that's the minus one2 in front of
the DC s by the
x^2 then there's plus Omega 2 x^2 so
that's plus Omega 2
x^2 Time s s is
eus Omega over 2x^2
and that we would like to be e *
s that we would like to be e time eus
Omega /
2x^2 okay let's examine the terms there
are two kinds of terms one of them has
x^2
eus Omega over 2x^2 in other words one
of them has an an X SAR sitting out in
front in fact there are two of them
these two both have
Omega 2 x^2 / 2 multiplying the wave
function but fortunately they cancel
because there would be nothing to cancel
them against in the rest of the equation
minus and plus so quite independently of
what the igen value is over here these
two
cancel we don't have to worry about them
they're
gone what's left what's left is 12 Omega
e- Omega 2
x^2 equal e * e- Omega 2x2 in other
words a certain constant times the
exponential is equal to another constant
times the exponential well it's quite
clear how to solve this you just set e
equal to 12
Omega e = 12 Omega that will solve the
equation so we found one igen vector of
the hamiltonian with IG value let's
let's summarize what we found over here
we found an igen Vector a single igen
Vector s of
x equals e to Theus what is it Omega / 2
X2 that corresponds to to an igen value
e equal to Omega over
2 let me go back and remind you why this
happens to be the ground state of the
oscillator this happens to be the state
of lowest energy you won't get any lower
energy than
that
uh
question um so go back to the classical
hiltonium there that you said it could
be zero because we would set p and X to
Zero over there yeah for the classical
for the classical right so when you talk
about the the uncertain principle does
that mean that that there'll never be a
zero energy State that's right there
will not be a zero energy State there
isn't the lowest energy this this
happens to be the lowest
energy there is no energy State lower
than
that it happens to be the
lowest uh so if you solve that equation
with d equal Z then say it again so if
you solve that equation with eal 0 would
blow up if you try that's right if you
try to solve it with E equals z you can
try you just sit down and Fiddle around
with it well then you get I Vector one I
Vector One S is equal to one
no no no no no um supposing you put in s
is equal to
one I'm just saying that's not Square
integral no but that's not the problem
it also doesn't solve the
equation put in s equals 1 that would
correspond to P equals
0 doesn't correspond to x equals 0 Let's
see yeah good all right so good point
let's put in s equals
1 why does he say s equals 1 s equals 1
is a state of zero momentum
okay zero momentum it doesn't oscillate
at all has no oscillations all right
let's try it out this would give zero
because after all it's just p^ s and if
the momentum is zero for that wave
function it just gives zero but this
doesn't give zero it gives X squ and
there's no way it can match against here
right if you try to solve this equation
with zero on the right it doesn't solve
for zero it doesn't solve for anything
if you try to solve the equation with E
equals z you can solve it but it will
simply blow up in both directions it'll
blow up in both directions or at least
one direction typically it will blow up
in both directions you can force it by
starting by starting out the right way
you can force it to zero in One
Direction but it will blow up in the
other direction
so E equals z is not a solution but the
other way to see it is just from the
shouting sorry from the uncertainty
principle that there can't be a state
with both p and x equal to Zer it would
violate the uncertainty principle are
you saying that for you have two two
solutions because it's second order
you're saying no linear combination of
those two solutions will will ever give
you say for E equals z will ever give
you a bounded uh right right that's
correct that's exactly right yeah leave
the blower you can by starting the
initial conditions tuning the initial
conditions you can make it go to zero in
One Direction but you'll find it blows
up in the other right now that's
typically the case with any arbitrary
value of the energy it's a certain now
we found one value of the energy
here I knew the solution so I plugged it
in but uh uh uh it is just a
differential equation you look at it
long enough and you see that e- x^2 will
solve it eus Omega 2x^2 will solve it
and that corresponds to an energy I
value which happens to be Omega over 2
possible to prove that this is the
lowest energy I can value I won't try to
do it right now there you said there's
two solutions what's the other solution
what's the other solution oh it blows up
like e to plus x s e to the Omega over
2x2 the same equation so usually we
would get a family of solutions from
this yeah you get a Family Solutions
which far away uh behave like a linear
combination of e to the-
x^2 when I say e to the- x^2 I'm
ignoring the Omega over 2 I mean once
you have a particular solution don't you
usually get a family of solutions from
that no if you have two solutions for a
linear equation you can add them
together with arbitrary coefficients and
find a solution find an arbitrary
solution okay so there are two linearly
independent
Solutions one looks like eus omeg over
2x^2 you can multiply it by any constant
and the other ASM totically looks like e
to the um uh plus Omega over
2x^2
yeah in this particular case the
solution which goes to zero in One
Direction also happens to go to zero in
the other direction but that doesn't
happen typically the typical s thing is
you have two independent Solutions one
of which goes to zero in One Direction
and blows up in the other and vice versa
and no combination will will uh uh will
work in both directions Omega you have
to put it positive there in order for
that to be yeah Omega
sorry on the other side e Omega has can
never be
negative say it again Omega must be
positive therefore yeah I mean right uh
in the original equation up there didn't
matter whether Omega was positive or
negative because Omega square is
positive all right so the correct
statement is if you want the wave
function to go to zero far away take the
positive root Prov yeah yeah yeah that
proves that's right good okay so the
ground state energy of the harmonic
oscillator is not zero it is Omega over
two if I wanted to put back H this is
incidentally not the dimensionally
consistent this is a frequency which
means a Radian per second or an inverse
time this is an energy if I want to get
back to dimensionally consistent
equations I have to put H bar back in
okay so in particular this means for any
kind of reasonable
frequency any kind of reasonable
frequency and that can mean very very
high frequencies enormously High the
energy will be very small because plunk
constant is very small so the energy of
the ground state is extremely
small and uh classically where we ignore
H bar it's just equal to
zero that's uh that's the way things go
okay now we want to see if we can find
more igen values but before we do that I
think we will take a break so that I can
have a little piece of
cookie all right incidentally this wave
function is not normalized the way it is
I don't remember what the normalization
factor is um
Square Ro of Omega and a square root of
Pi you can figure it out but
uh uh there's some numerical coefficient
that should go in front of it if you
want it to be square integrated to
one
okay I put zero here size zero in order
to indicate not that it's zero energy
but that it's the ground
state zero indicates ground state here
this is the wave function associated
with the ground state all right now in
order
to figure out the rest of the energy
levels we use some tricks and the tricks
uh the tricks are specific to the
harmonic
oscillator but they
um well let's put it this way they're
important is the tricks of constructing
creation and annihilation
operators operators which increase the
energy and operators which decrease the
energy so let me show you how that
works um
begin with the hamiltonian in the
form p^
2 /
two well first of all 1/2 let's take the
factor of 1/2 outside
1/2 p
2 plus Omega 2
x^2 now that's the classical hamiltonian
it's also the quantum mechanical
hamiltonian let me do a
manipulation which is fair and
correct uh for classical physics but
which requires a little modification for
quantum mechanics so here's the
manipulation this is the sums of squares
so we can rewrite this as 1/2 the sums
of squares I'm just going to use a 2 + b
2 is equal to a +
I time what is it a uh a 2 + b 2 * a
minus I now do I have that right yeah I
have that right a
2 - * I * I is plus b^ 2 and the cross
term cancels out okay so let's write
this in the form um p
plus I Omega
X time P minus I Omega
X I haven't done anything I've just
Rewritten the sums of squares in a
different
form but now I'm going to give these
guys names P plus I Omega X and P minus
I Omega X they're essentially creation
and Annihilation
operators they're not quite because I
don't have the right coefficient in
front of them but we'll we'll figure out
what the right coefficient as we go
along the creation and Annihilation
operators which we we'll see what they
do we'll figure out what they do what
Their definition is but
um now which one is
which which one increases the energy and
which one decreases the energy a trick
question the minus increases yeah I
think it's the minus
yeah
maybe yeah I know
but I'm not sure let's let's assume all
right so let's call this one and if it
doesn't work we'll figure out we'll just
interchange it let's call this one
B+ that's terrible calling a thing with
a minus sign
B+ I'm going to call it B minus and the
chances are we're going to regret it
let's call it B minus just because it
has the minus sign in
here all right and let's call this one
B+ okay now strictly speaking in quantum
mechanics B+ * B minus is not equal to P
^2 + Omega 2 x^2 and the reason has to
do with the
non-computational like this if we tried
to write that let's forget this for a
minute
um oh I know where I know where the
factors go but let's all right if I try
to write the hamiltonian like this let's
work it out this would give me first of
all p^ s it would give me
12 p ^ 2 p * p is p ^
2 it would give me plus Omega 2 x^2 when
I multiply this out plus Omega 2 x^2
that's good P yeah that's right it's the
XP and the PX ones which are a little
bit problematic so from on then it would
give me plus I
Omega and then we would have XP from
here let's put a bracket around it XP
from here minus PX from the other
one now I'm keeping careful track of the
order of things we have x to the left
here P to the right here so that's XP
and here we have p on the left X on the
right they come in with opposite signs
classically this would just go
away but Quantum mechanically the
commutator of X and P is not equal to
zero uh what was the commutator of X and
p
i i h bar right so since we' set H bar
equal to zero no we've set H bar equal
to one
we can just say that the commutator here
is I I * I here is minus1 so it looks to
me like uh this whole thing here is
12 p^ 2 +
X2 plus Omega 2
x^2
plus plus or minus om minus Omega right
Justus
omegaus
omegaus Omega over
2 I've taken into account the F the
factor of a half here so the right thing
to write then this here is not p^2 +
Omega 2 x^2 it differs from p^2 + Omega
2 x^2 by Omega / 2 all right so if I
really want write this Quantum
mechanically I think I have to add yes I
have to add plus Omega over 2
right did I do it
right
okay all right but this is just a
constant this is just a
constant it adds into every igen value
Omega over
two but if we can find the igen values
of p plus I Omega * P minus I Omega
that's good enough because we just add
to every igen value Omega over two in
other words this here is just a number
it's not an interesting operator if you
take any operator and add an ordinary
number to it it just shifts all the en
values by a common amount it shifts all
the igen values by the same amount now
what is this this is just a Zero Point
Energy this is the Zero Point Energy the
same thing that we found over here Omega
over
two so we've written the hamiltonian in
the form of a ground state energy plus
something else it had better be that
when we that this thing when it applies
to the ground state gives zero right
because we've already got the ground
state energy here
explicitly so let's check that let's
first
check that this
object as it stands
here that this
piece has igen value zero when it's
applied to the ground state wave
function let's do that exercise first
okay here we are here's our
hamiltonian let me rewrite it put it up
here H =
12 p + I Omega x * P minus I Omega
X notice these are hermiss conjugates of
each other
other P plus I Omega X is the Herm
Mission
conjugate classically it would just be
complex conjugate they're the Herm
missan conjugates of each
other but good enough that uh oh sorry
plus Omega over 2 plus Omega over
two okay that's that's our starting
point okay let's apply P minus I Omega x
to the wave function and then multiply
it by P plus r Omega X and try to check
whether we get zero as I said we should
get zero because we already have the
ground state energy
here okay so P minus I Omega x what is p
p is minus i d by
DX minus I Omega
X multiplied by eus Omega / 2x^2
multiplied simply means you do the
operation
okay
um yeah that looks right yeah good okay
now let's take out the factor minus
I minus
I
and was this plus I think it was plus
then
right yeah minus i d by DX - I Omega X
both of them have the same sign minus I
in front of them okay what happens when
we
differentiate once eus Omega over
2x^2 any uh let's see can I remember
yeah it just gives us
minus Omega
X eus Omega over 2x^2
right no
um yes
no no differentiating the X squ gives me
a two and that eats this two
here right okay no no
two all right so the first term just
gives me minus Omega x e to Theus Omega
over 2x^2 and the second term just gives
me plus the same thing so I don't even
have to go I don't even have to worry
about the second Factor here the first
Factor when it hits the wave function or
already gives me
zero okay so that
guarantees that when the product of
these hits the wave function we get zero
and this is the only thing left over
good so we've checked yeah we're doing
something right
this wave function satisfies the right
property okay these two seem to be
interesting op
objects and one first of all the
hamiltonian has been reduced to the form
of something times its complex conjugate
or it's Herm Mission conjugate second
this object uh annihilates the ground
state the terminology is it annihilates
the ground state let's explore these two
objects a little bit
more let's give them a name I think I
will call this one B
minus and this one B+ yeah
okay so this one is B
minus and this one is
B+ first of all B+ and B minus are Herm
mission conjugates of each other
classically complex conjugates of each
other okay so that's a good that's an
interesting fact next they have some
interesting commutation relations let's
compute the commutator of B+ with B
minus
let's compute it and see what we get
just for fun uh they're not observables
incidentally why aren't they
observables because the individual ones
are not her Mission they're not
observables they're not her Mission they
don't have a complete set in general
they don't have a complete set of igen
vectors but nevertheless let's figure
out we're going to do some algebra with
them it will be useful to know what the
commutator is when we start multiplying
them in various ways it will be useful
okay so what is this this is a
commutator of p + I Omega
x with P minus I Omega
X we start working out the commutator
the commutator of p with p is
zero the commutator what about the
commutator of I Omega x with
P well come Ator of X with p is I
right so the commutator of these
two let the commutator of these two
here will give us I Omega time another I
in other words minus
Omega the commutator of p with minus I
Omega X well the commutator of p with X
is minus I commutator of X with p is I
commutator of p with X is minus I but
there's another minus here it just gives
the whole thing just gives two
Omega two Omega for the whole
thing so the commutator between B+ and B
minus is just 2
Omega 2
Omega all right this is It's perfectly
okay the opp operate with B+ and B
minus it's a matter of definition and a
matter of history and a matter of uh
convention to divide B+ and B minus by
the square root of 2 Omega and call the
result
a all right so B
/ Square < TK of 2 Omega is called
A+ and B minus over < TK of 2 Omega is
called a minus
and then what's the commutator of A+
with a minus one all I've did was divide
this out so that the commutator would be
one now as I said this is somewhat a
matter of convention it's it is a matter
of convention it's it's a nice
convention we'll see but nevertheless
it's just a convention to Define A+ and
a minus so that the commutator is
one one
all right once we've done that we can
now rewrite the hamiltonian in terms of
A+ and a minus in terms of the B's let's
rewrite this in terms of the B's it's 12
B+ B minus that's p+ I Omega P minus I
Omega X B+ B minus plus Omega /
2 that's what it was here but supposing
I substitute in the
A's I'm going to have instead of B+ B
minus I'm going to have A+ a minus times
a factor of 2
Omega okay so this is going to just be
just simple it's hardly even in the
algebra just substitute solve for the
B's squ > 2
Omega squ > of 2
Omega a
minus all right and now substitute for
the B's in terms of the A's and what do
we get I think we get Omega a + a
minus plus Omega / 2 there it
is Omega a + a
minus +
12 so we've reduced the problem of the
harmonic oscillator the problem of
finding the energy levels and the igen
igen vectors but in particular the
energy levels to
finding the igen values of an operator
A+ a
minus
given that A+ and a minus have a
commutator equal to one we now have
basically an algebra
problem
uh or a very very simple operator
problem let's condense it over over on
this side here here it
is find the igen
values of A+ a
minus the half here just shifts all the
igen values we don't care about that at
the end of the day we'll add a half to
all of them we'll also multiply the
result by
Omega that's not interesting
find the igen values e
values of A+ a
minus
given that the commutator of A+ with a
minus is equal to 1 now did I get the
sign right I wasn't very careful when I
was doing it um anybody having there
could go look quickly through the notes
it's either plus one or minus
one
uh I wasn't careful I should have been
more
careful let's see
um I'm
think
um I think somewhere is along I I I have
a a wrong sign and it could be in any
number of places - 2
Omega minus 2 Omega no I guess not I
don't think so it could easily be that I
have a wrong definition that this should
be called a
minus somebody thought that H somebody
had proposed that oh well that may be
right yeah that may be right it may be
that what I called A+ I now regret and
should call A minus of course it is
purely a
convention all right but H memory from
memory I remember that the commutator
let's see of A+ with a minus should be
oh wait uh A+ a minus a minus
A+ should be minus one yeah okay I think
I have a definition wrong the correct
definition should
be um that this is called a
minus no no no no no no no no I think no
no I have it
right why don't you just put it Asus
yeah I think it should be minus one I
don't know where I I don't know where I
lost uh the uh sign let's just keep
going we'll find out if it should be
minus one or plus one um commutata of a
plus with a minus I think is minus
one and that's just something I recall
from having done this many many times
before okay you were Computing the car
you said um that the first term is
supposed to be negative Omega and then
you were subtracting another Omega so it
should be -2 Omega which you then fold
into the A and you get minus one okay
good you you you you say it should be
minus
one let's not press all luck let's just
say it's
minus1 and with uh somebody having
uh and if it turns out wrong we'll find
out okay um that's our problem A+ a
minus =
minus1 good now let me show you
something that if I
take a igen vector let's call it
o this is supposed to represent the
ground state this is the ground state
what is the igen vector of a plus a
minus for the ground
state one no zero sorry zero z0 zero
remember the ground state was a minus
gave zero when it hit the ground state
okay so a minus on the ground
state is equal to zero that was just
this little calculation where we took uh
P minus I Omega X
and multiplied it by E to Theus Omega
over 2x^2 we got zero okay so a minus on
the ground state is equal to zero first
uh first fact this now incidentally this
does not represent the igen value of the
energy obviously it doesn't the igen
value of the energy is Omega over two it
just represents ground state the first
state we could have called it one for
the first state but we call it zero for
the for the ground state for the V for
the ground state let's just call it
ground state okay A minus on this is
equal to
zero let what about
A+ let's take A+ on zero that's some new
state we can figure out exactly what its
wave function is and we will do it later
but let's see what its energy is it may
not be an igen Vector of energy there's
no guarantee that that that it's an igen
Vector of energy but it is let's just
check it how do we check that this is an
igen Vector of the
energy right we simply or an igen Vector
better yet of A+ a minus well we just
multiply it by a plus a minus let's put
a bracket around it A+ a
minus if this object is an igen Vector
of this operator what does it mean it
means that this is equal to some number
Lambda times the original vector which
was A+ on
o in other words I'm asking the question
let's just take it as a question is this
an igen Vector of the energy and if so
what energy let's call or what igen
value so of a plus a minus let's call it
Lambda I now take not the commutator
this is not the commutator it's just the
product I'm getting a little tired and
I'm starting to make mistakes A+ a minus
hitting A+ on zero may or may not give
us some constant time A Plus on Z is it
clear why this is the igen value
condition for A+ 0 A Plus on
Zer if not raise it right now and
know I assume that the lack of response
means uh yes that it's
clear okay
now here I have if I now remove the
bracket I have
A+ a minus A+ on
zero what I want to do is I want to
Interchange the order of these two let's
interchange the order of these two but
I'm not allowed to do that the only I'm
not allowed to do it because they don't
commute but what I can do is I can say
that a + a
minus uh - a - A+ is equal to -
1 and so the point is I can take a plus
here let's rewrite it A+ a minus + 1 is
equal to Aus
A+ All right I have a minus A+ here I
can replace it by A+ a minus but I have
to add in a one so let's do that this is
equal to
A+ right times
A+ a
minus +
one on
o all I've done is use the commutation
relation to invert the order of these
two and
then add in the extra one that's
necessary
there okay now A minus on zero gives
zero so A minus on Z gives Z this can be
ignored and what do we get we just get
A+ on
Z this is a fairly long story but what
it said is that A+ a minus multiplying
this Vector
here just gives
one times the same
Vector the
conclusion this new Vector here is an
igen Vector of A+ a minus with igen
value not equal to zero but igen value
one right let's go back to the
hamiltonian to the energy we have found
a second igen Vector of the
hamiltonian which is equal to A+ on o
we'll figure out what its wave function
in is in a moment but the energy
associated with it is Omega the energy
is Omega * 1 +
12 3es three Hales Omega where's the
three Hales come from well we found out
that this new state Vector is an igen
Vector of a plus a minus with igen value
one so I just plug in one for A+ a
minus in other words by acting with the
operator A+ on the ground state we have
added one unit of energy measured in
units of Omega we've added one unit of
energy to the ground state that's what
we've
done well what happens if we do it
again let's try to see what happens if
we do it
again in fact supposing we
have an igen vector of a plus a minus
with igen value
n in other words supposing we have found
a solution a + a
minus on some Vector which I'll call
n is equal to n * n now you might get
the idea that I'm thinking that n is an
integer and I am but at the moment I
have no need to assume n is an integer
it's just a number this is an igen
Vector here is its igen value by
definition may or may not be an integer
supposing we have found one now we found
two such things we found two already we
found one in which n is equal to zero
and we found one in which n is equal to
1 and they were related to each other by
increasing n by applying A+ this is very
general let's see if we can see
why all right
let's invent n +
one this is only its name it doesn't
really mean necessarily yet that it has
igen value n plus one it's just its name
and it's just gotten by
definition A+ on N assumption n is an
igen Vector of A+ a minus with igen
value n right too many ends but you get
the idea let's see what A+ a minus does
when it hits n +
one let's see if this is really an igen
Vector well all we have to do is take A+
a minus A+ on
N right so far do I have it right yeah
we just do the same thing we did before
yeah
okay what uh good what do we do we
interchange the order of these two right
we get the substitute A+ a minus + 1 for
a minus we get a plus a minus + one is
that
right
yeah and then the left the left hand one
goes
away cuz a minus on N
is Aus is what no no no no no no you see
yeah a plus a minus on
N yeah a plus a minus on N is just equal
to little n * n so the whole thing is
just equal
to n +
1 as
this time n +
1 times the igen vector n+1 the IG
Vector n +1 is just a + * n get it this
is just n Plus + one that's sorry yeah
that's what this says and then A Plus on
N gives us the I Vector n plus one do
the algebra do the algebra all right
here's the upshot here's the uh here's
the
theorem that if you have an igen Vector
with igen value n of a plus a minus and
you hit that igen Vector with
A+ to create a new igen Vector a new
Vector then that new Vector is also an
Vector of A+ a minus with igen value n +
one this has igen
value n + one I don't know how to write
this I'm getting tired and I'm losing it
but I think you get the
idea the creation operator or this plus
operator A+ acts on any igen Vector of
A+ a minus to raise the igen value by
one okay raises the value by one the
result is that the spectrum of igen
values
starts at 1
12 spectrum of igen values of the energy
starts at Omega over
2 operating with
A+ adds one unit which means it becomes
three halves
Omega hit it again it becomes 5 Hales
Omega and so forth and so on and the
spectrum of energies is
Omega * n + a
half now relative to the ground state
it's just Omega
n so if we threw away the ground state
energy if we threw it away and say
that's always there then these raising
operators simply add an in integer
multiple of Omega and strictly speaking
it's h Omega it's h Omega energy each
time it acts good so here's
the here are all the igen vectors of the
energy start with o what is o o
is the abstract Vector associated with
this multiply it by A+
multiply it twice by
A+ multiply
it any number of
times by
A+ and what you make is the sequence of
energy levels Omega over
Omega 3 * Omega / 2 5 * Omega over 2 and
so forth you know what I mean
uh Omega * 12 Omega * 3 Hal and so
forth okay so that is the complete
solution of the harmonic
oscillator and it explains why the
energy of oscillations is quantized
quantized in units of the frequency
times plunks constant Omega * HR is the
unit of energy each time you raise the
energy level by A+ you raise the energy
by Omega H bar as I said Omega H bar is
typically a very very small
energy okay are there any questions uh
now about the harmonic
oscillator yeah are there any other
hamiltonians that have equally spaced no
no well yes I take that
back I take that back there are there is
another there are other hamiltonians
which have equally SPAC there's one
other one it has not only positive
energy levels it has negative energy
levels
uh and uh it's just the angular momentum
itself angular momentum comes in units
of uh of H bar Omega oh sorry in units
of har bar and it can be plus or minus
any integer and if you took for the
hamiltonian the angular momentum itself
now why you would want to do that what
kind of system that would be would be a
little strange system energy is equal to
angular momentum but uh it's a possible
hamiltonian and yes it would have
equally spaced energy levels but they
would go from plus infinity all the way
down to minus infinity so
um uh this is the only one which has a
spectrum which is bounded From Below
which has a minimum energy level that
has integer energy levels and a bottom a
bottom a ground state then it's a harm
oscillator okay so
uh good any other questions yeah so
question so what uh physically this
system would be would it be like a maybe
like an electron moving away from a
charge plate or something like that how
would you you got to have something that
restores the movement right the
restoring force in it what Quantum
harmonic look like what say it again
what does a Quantum harmonic
what do you mean what does it look like
doesn't look like anything you can't see
it I mean what Quantum systems don't
look like
anything I'm not sure what the question
is but is it like an an electron going
around an AC or no the electron going
around in an atom is not a harmonic
oscillator um the reason all right when
do you get harmonic
oscillators or approximate harmonic
oscillators
go ahead diatomic molecule oh a diatomic
molecule is a very good example yeah but
there's a very general rule if you have
some potential energy for a
problem which has a minimum and it could
be a function of any number of variables
but let's suppose it's a function only
of one variable for
Simplicity then if there's a stability
point the point at which there stability
that means that the potential energy has
some minimum someplace
so I don't care what the problem is
there's some problem in which there's a
potential energy function and the
potential energy has a minimum any
function which has a typical function
which has a minimum near that minimum
will look like a
parabola unless of course you
artificially tune the X squ term away a
typical situation the general situation
uh except for some very special
fine-tune situations is if you have a
function with a minimum that if you look
nearby the minimum it looks like a
parabola right a parabola means that
nearby the minimum if I study the system
as a in terms of deviations away from
the minimum let's call that variable X
deviation from the minimum the energy
the potential energy will look like X
squ if there's a stable point that means
if you displace it a little bit it will
be pulled back to the origin
that's the assumption that there's a
stable solution so if there's any kind
of stable solution it will get pulled
back to the origin that's what stability
means uh if you pull it the other way
it'll get pulled back to the origin and
it becomes a harmonic oscillator so all
kinds of systems so as was mentioned if
you have a diatomic molecule just two
atoms and there's some
stable um configuration of the atom of
the molecu
then small
deviations will oscillate about the but
they'll Quantum mechanically oscillate
I'm not sure what it means to ask what
does a quantum mechanical system look
like if you try toig find out what it
looks like by hitting it with a photon
you disturb it and it's not possible to
really take a photograph of a quantum
mechanical system without disturbing it
so it's a bad question what does a
quantum mechanical system look like on
the the other hand we can ask what the
various energy levels what the
probability distribution for them looks
like all right the ground state the
probability
distribution is a gaussian a bell-shaped
curve with a width which is controlled
by Omega the bigger Omega gets the
narrower the
distribution the distribution has a
width which is controlled by Omega why
does the width get narrow with Omega
well if you go back to the
original uh definition of what Omega is
Omega is associated the square of Omega
is the spring constant right the tighter
the spring
constant the more tightly the oscillator
is held to the
origin all right the more tightly it's
held to the origin the less spread the
wave function will have so that's the
character of this the bigger Omega the
less the spread of the wave
function
but apart from its spread it's just
given by a bell-shaped curve by a
gaussian function of X gaussian means
eus X squar all right let's go to the
next energy level let's see if we can
find out what the next energy level
looks like it's actually easy all we
have to
do is say that the next energy level is
given by A+ on o now what was A+ do we
have A+ written down someplace
um I lost it it
was P plus I Omega X or P minus I Omega
X not sure we have
Noone I think it was it should be P
minus I Omega X oh here it is here it is
it
yeah but that was the mistake that we
made that should be that should be B+
and that I think we said this was right
no no we this was right you don't get
the minus one yeah we do no you don't
because when you when you did the
commutator you made a
mistake go yeah why don't we just work
it out this way and if it comes out the
answer comes out bad then you know okay
you want to do you want to do it
all no no he watch go forward go forward
assuming your way what's that forward
assuming I'm wrong no move
on all right there's an easy way to tell
if this is a
minus it should annihilate the ground
state which it do which it does so this
is a minus okay end of
story yeah good so this moment must be
A+ good or B+ doesn't matter A+ or B+
okay so let's then take
the ground state eus Omega over 2x^2 and
hit it with
B+ we should find the next energy level
let's see what the wave function looks
like so B+ is 1 12 forget the 1 12
there's no one2 B+ is min - i d by
DX
plus I Omega
X that's B+ where I've used minus i d by
DX for p now hit that with e to Theus
Omega / 2x^2 what do we
get okay as I
remember let's first of all take out the
factor of
I minus d by DX gives us what Omega
gives us a factor of minus Omega X right
both of these give us Omega
X both of them give us Omega X so apart
from a factor of I which we can put in
and a factor of two which we can put in
it's
x with an Omega X eus Omega /
2x^2 the factor of 2 and I and Omega
that's just a multiplicative constant
the wave function looks like the
gaussian multiplied by X all right
that's a function
which ASM totically still goes to zero
this way eus Omega uh Omega over 2 x^2
goes to zero much faster than x
grows so it still goes very quickly to
zero but now it has a it looks like this
it has a zero in the middle here let me
make it more precise let me try to draw
it better it looks like
this it's Z at xal 0 Z it has one node a
node is just a place where it crosses
the real axis where it crosses the uh
the axis so that's the wave function of
the first excited state it's zero at the
origin and it uh and uh far away it
looks uh pretty much like a gaussian
down what the is it upside down
yeah
yeah mul mly by minus in fact it's not
just upside down it has a factor of I
missing and Omega okay yeah just throw
this away it's a constant and put a
minus in and that's it good okay each
time you try this out try go to the next
one go to the next one you just take uh
what do you do you take you take this
one which is X eus Omega over
2x^2 and you do it again minus i d by
DX d by DX Plus Omega
X all right the Omega X is going to give
you an X squ that's pretty clear the
minus i d by DX is going to give you two
terms one of them will come from hitting
here and it'll give you another Omega X
and the other one will hit this it's
quite clear what you're going to get as
a polom a quadratic
polom right all right each time you hit
it you create another zero
the next one would look something like
this two
zeros and would be the gaussian times a
polom with
sorry like
this would have two zeros each time you
raise you go you add one more zero you
go from Sy this is an anti-symmetric
wave function anti- symmetric means the
opposite sign on the two sides
you go back and forth from symmetric to
anti-symmetric to symmetric to anti-
symmetric and you add one more zero so
what happens is you start to get things
which oscillate more and more
rapidly that corresponds to putting in
more
momentum rapidly oscillating wave
functions indicate momentum well that's
not surprising you hit the oscillator
and you excite it to a high level of
excitation it's going to be whizzing
back and forth the whizzing back and
forth means that there's going to be
short wavelengths in the problem the
harder you hit it the more uh the more
there's going to be large momentum in
the wave function what's more it's going
to sort of spread out it's always going
to be ASM totically
small but it will spread out and do
things like this so what this
corresponds to is when you hit it it
hard you spread the wave function out
over a bigger distance corresponding to
the fact that it swings way out and
swings way out in the opposite direction
and you give it a lot of oscillation
indicating that you've given it a lot of
momentum so it's kind of fun to work out
the first uh five or six wave functions
and see how they look they look they
start to look more and more like
this and uh that's the harmonic
oscillator
the main thing is that the energy levels
are
quantized and that you go from energy
level to energy level by these
operations here the A+ operation
incidentally as you might expect if you
take a wave function with a given energy
and you apply the lowering operator the
a minus as you might expect that lowers
the energy down one unit until you get
down to the ground state when you get
down to the round State a minus gives
you zero nothing left there so that's
the character of the harmonic oscillator
we did not get to angular
momentum at some point in this course of
lectures when we get to Quantum field
Theory I will discuss angular momentum
for you so that's the harmonic
oscillator any questions are the are the
zeros the pols for real values what's
that say it again say ask
again I who's saying I Wasing that okay
yeah are the zeros the pols for real
values real values of X yes
yes uh is it
[Music]
obvious not completely no it's not
obviously obvious but it is
obvious no it's not obvious to me right
now uh right
uh yeah I I think it wouldn't be too
hard to to demonstrate but at the moment
I'm tired and it's not obvious to me no
but it's true so about the ground state
there are some values of X for which the
probability is zero there some values
that cannot yeah there's uh there's
that's right there's this this this
points where the probability is
zero right if you look for the particle
a you won't find it right weird huh
nevertheless the particle goes swinging
back and forth and some horm monic
oscillator
sense right destructive interference at
those
points another question is is there any
meaning in
asking why do we have quanti States or
is it just why do we have quanti energy
basically I just show you yeah I know
but okay but it seems to me that the
mathematics is fitting something no it
doesn't this isn't the kind of the cause
of of of saying is the C oh I suppose
somebody wants some physical
justification for square inability or
something you don't always have states
do you you can have a continuous set of
alides like on your free part only
only typically you don't get a
continuous set if the particle is
confined in some potential that keeps it
uh
uh yeah there are times when you get
continuous energy levels and uh
basically it's when the particle is free
to move off ASM totically without being
uh see this the harmonic oscillator the
particle no matter how much energy you
give it is never free to asymptotically
fly away from the system it's always
pulled back the wave functions are
concentrated when the wave functions are
concentrated you are going to get uh
discrete energy levels
always than skape velocity
that's that's that's essentially right
yeah yeah when the when the momentum or
when the energy is above the Escape
energy let's call it when the energy is
above the Escape energy then you have
continuous energy levels right what what
I I suppose the question he was asking
is why are why are the functions that
the solutions that blow up excluded
excludable why don't they can't they
haveen well where where in that case the
particle has all of its probability
infinitely far
away in other words if you normalize the
wave function if you normalize the wave
function then all the probability is
infinitely far
away probability of finding it in any
finite place is
zero so okay perfectly good nothing
wrong with it except you'll never find
the particle so let's throw it away
exactly okay yeah
it also has Infinite Energy because the
in because the potential energy will be
infinite since it's a
right um no we probably NE I probably
never spelled it out but strictly
speaking the way the state vectors of a
properly defined quantum mechanical
system have to be
normalizable that means that the
integral of s star s should or the sum
or whatever it is should be able to add
up to
one a probability distribution what
you've just said though is more
satisfying than then the other way is to
just make it that be an axium yeah you
can make it be an axiom and it's a true
Axiom it's a good Axiom but if you ask
why do you make that
axium uh well it forbids these systems
where the particle is has zero
probability of being found anywhere in
the finite region of space yeah yeah
that's that's right
okay all right next time we will go on
to field
Theory I can take my oh I don't have to
write new notes for next
[Music]
time the proceeding program is
copyrighted by Stanford University
please visit us at stanford.edu